Inventory of the John W. Lewis and Lewis P. Olds Papers, 1808-1900s
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
John W. Lewis and Lewis P. Olds Papers 1808-1900s
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
2010.022
1 Cubic Foot
Lewis, John W. ([1808]-1885); Latting, Sally; Olds, Lewis P.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased on 1/20/2010.
Biographical Information
John W. Lewis was raised in Randolph County, North Carolina. In 1833, at around the age of 25, Lewis entered the Virginia Conference of Methodist ministers. His 50+ year career as a pastor took him from Virginia to Mississippi and eventually back to his home state of North Carolina. Lewis was a slave-owning member of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MEC-S) offshoot that split from the main Methodist Episcopal Church due to differing views on the issue of slavery. He died on May 23, 1885.
Lewis P. Olds was a North Carolina lawyer and politician. He served as the state's Attorney General from 1869-1870, as State Senator from 1870-1871, and as the United States consul to St. Helena from 1876-1877.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of three Southerners, dating predominantly from the 19th century. John W. Lewis lived in Virginia, Mississippi, and North Carolina and the portion of the collection from this Methodist minister and farmer includes references to religion including sermons, farming, and slavery. Lewis P. Olds was a North Carolina lawyer and politician and the collection includes evidence of his career as well as poetry and short stories he wrote. The remainder of the collection is schoolwork of Sally Latting from 1808 and unattributed photographs and a recipe book.
Index Terms
Subjects:
North Carolina--History--19th century--Sources; North Carolina--Social life and customs--19th century; Slavery--North Carolina--History.; Slavery--Virginia--History--19th century.; Virginia--History--19th century--Sources; Virginia--Social life and customs--19th century
Genre and Form Terms:
Broadsides; Correspondence; Photographs; Poems; Recipes; Sermons
Detailed Description of the Collection
- John W. Lewis 1840-1885
  This series consists of the correspondence and personal papers of John W. Lewis, a North Carolina-born Methodist minister and slave-owning farmer. Subjects of correspondence include religion, family matters, farming, and slavery. Included in Lewis' personal papers are two drafts of his last will and testament, property tax assessments from Mississippi, and an August 1875 ballot for the appointment of delegates to the Constitutional Convention.
  - John W. Lewis Correspondence 1840-1885 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - John W. Lewis Correspondence 1840-1885 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - John W. Lewis Personal Papers 1840-1885 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Lewis P. Olds 1840-1900
  This series consists of the correspondence and personal papers of Lewis P. Olds, a North Carolina attorney and politician. Subjects of correspondence primarily deal with Olds' work as an attorney, as Attorney General of North Carolina, and as State Senator of North Carolina. Olds' personal papers are made up primarily of a number of short stories, poems, and epic poems that he authored.
  - Lewis P. Olds Correspondence 1840-1900 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Lewis P. Olds Correspondence 1840-1900 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Lewis P. Olds Correspondence 1840-1900 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Lewis P. Olds Poetry 1840-1900 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Lewis P. Olds Poetry 1840-1900 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Lewis P. Olds Poetry 1840-1900 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Lewis P. Olds Poetry 1840-1900 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Lewis P. Olds Poetry 1840-1900 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Miscellaneous 1808-circa 1900
  This series consists of schoolwork done by Sally Latting in 1808. Also included in this series are a number of unidentifiable or unattributable items from the collection, including photographs and recipe books.
  - Sally Latting Schoolwork 1808 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Photographs circa 1800-1900 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Recipe Books circa 1800-1900 (Box-folder 2:3)